<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>His Majesties answer to the petition of the Lords and Commons in Parliament assembled: presented to His Majestie at York, June 17. 1642.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78656</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C2137</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E152_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16799</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860096</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860096</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156781</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78656)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156781)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 27:E152[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>His Majesties answer to the petition of the Lords and Commons in Parliament assembled: presented to His Majestie at York, June 17. 1642.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I)</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Barker, Printer to the Kings most Excellent Majestie: And by the Assignes of John Bill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes the text of the petition.</note>
                  <note>In this edition the first two words of title are in capital and small capital letters, except for the "j" in "Majesties" which is in lower case.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales --  Parliament. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:156781:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>HIS MAJESTIES ANSWER TO THE PETITION OF The LORDS and COMMONS in Parliament aſſembled: Preſented to His Majeſtie at YORK, June 17. 1642.</p>
            <p>LONDON: Printed by ROBERT BARKER, Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſtie: And by the Aſſignes of JOHN BILL. 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:156781:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:156781:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Kings moſt Excellent Majestie</hi> The humble Petition of the Lords and Commons in Parliament aſſembled.</head>
            <p>YOur Majeſties moſt humble and faithfull Subjects, the Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parliament, have late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly received a Petition from a great number of the Gentry, Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders and other inhabitants of the County of <hi>York,</hi> aſſembled there by Your Majeſties Command the third of June, wherein they declare unto us, <hi>That having taken a reſolution to addreſſe themſelves unto Your Majeſtie in the humble way of a Petition, for the redreſſe of thoſe Grievances which they now lie under, they were violently interrupted and affronted therein by the Earle of</hi> Lyndſey, <hi>the Lord</hi> Savill <hi>and others, and notwithſtanding all the means they could uſe to preſent their juſt deſires to Your Majeſtie, yet they could not prevail with Your Majeſtie to accept of their Petition;</hi> The Copie whereof they have ſent to us, with an humble Deſire, <hi>That we would take ſuch courſe therein as may tend to the Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Liberties, and the Peace of the Kingdom; And that we would addreſſe our ſelves to Your Majeſtie in their behalf, that by our means their deſires may finde better acceptation with Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie;</hi> Whereupon, having ſeriouſly weighed, and conſidered the particulars of thoſe their Complaints and Deſires, as they are laid down in their Petition; And finding that the Grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces they complain of are the increaſe of the Miſeries formerly ſuſtained by that Countie (which hath well-nigh for three veers laſt paſt been the Tragicall Stage of Armies and War) by reaſon of Your Majeſties diſtance in Reſidence, and differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in Counſels from your great Councell, the Parliament, begetting great diſtempers and diſtractions thorowout the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:156781:3"/>Kingdom, and eſpecially in that Countie; The drawing to thoſe Parts great numbers of diſcontented Perſons, that may too juſtly be feared do affect the publike Ruine for their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate advantage; The drawing together of many Companies of the Trained Bands, and others both Horſe and Foot of that Countie, and retaining multitudes of Commanders and Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers from other parts; The daily reſort of Recuſants to Your Majeſties Court at <hi>York;</hi> The great preparations of Arms and other warlike Proviſions, to the great terrour and amazement of Your Majeſties peaceable Subjects, and cauſing a great decay of Trade and Commerce amongſt them. All and every of which particulars are againſt the Law, which Your Majeſtie hath made ſo many and ſo frequent Profeſſions to uphold and maintain. And the Lords and Commons finding on the other ſide their humble deſires to be, That Your Majeſtie would hearken to Your Parliament, and declining all other Counſells whatſoever, unite your Confidence to Your Parliament, and that Your Majeſtie would not divide Your Subjects joynt dutie to Your Majeſtie, the Parliament and Kingdom, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Eſſence of Your great Councell and higheſt Court, by ſubjecting the Determinations and Counſells thereof to the Counſells and Opinions of any private perſons whatſoever; That Your Majeſtie having paſſed an Act, That this Parliament ſhall not be diſſolved, but by Act of Parliament, Your Majeſty would not do any thing tending thereunto, by commanding away the Lords and great Officers, whoſe attendance is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary thereunto; That Your Majeſtie having expreſſed Your confidence in the affections of that Countie, You would pleaſe to diſmiſſe Your extraordinary Guards, and the Cavaliers and others of that qualitie, who ſeem to have little Intereſt or Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to the publike good, their language and behaviour ſpeaking nothing but Diviſion and War, and their advantage conſiſting in that which is moſt deſtructive to others. And
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:156781:3"/>laſtly, that in ſuch Conſultations and Propoſitions as Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie maketh to that Countie, ſuch may not be thruſt upon them as men of that Countie, that neither by their fortune or reſidence are any part of it.</p>
            <p>All which their humble and moſt juſt deſires being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Law, which Your Majeſtie hath ſo often declared ſhould be the Meaſure and Rule of Your Government and Actions; And we Your Majeſties moſt faithfull Subjects the Lords and Commons fully concurring with the Gentlemen and others of the Countie of <hi>York</hi> in their Aſſurance that thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of theirs will abundantly redound to the glory of God, the honour and ſafety of Your Majeſtie, the good of Your Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, and the Peace and Proſperity of this Kingdom; we humbly beſeech Your Majeſtie graciouſly to hearken unto them, and to grant them; and that you would joyn with Your Parliament in a ſpeedy and effectuall courſe for the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of their Liberties, and the Peace of the Kingdom, which dutie, as we are now called upon by that Countie to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge, ſo do we ſtand engaged to God and man for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance thereof by the truſt repoſed in us, and by our ſolemn Vow and Proteſtation; And Your Majeſtie, together with us, ſtands engaged by the like Obligation of truſt, and of an Oath, beſides the many and earneſt Profeſſions and Proteſtations, which Your Majeſtie hath made to this Purpoſe to Your whole Kingdom in generall, and to that Countie in particular; the Peace and quiet of the Kingdom (as is well obſerved by theſe Gentlemen and Free-holders of <hi>Yorkſhire</hi> in their Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) being the onely viſible means under God, wherein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts the Preſervation of the Proteſtant Religion, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of our brethren in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the happineſſe and proſperity of Your Majeſtie, and of all Your Dominions.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:156781:4"/>
            <head>His MAJESTIES Anſwer to the Petition of the Lords and Commons in Parliament aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, preſented to His MAJESTIE at Yorke, <hi>the</hi> 17 <hi>of</hi> June. 1642.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Is Majeſtie having carefully weighed the matter of this Petition preſented to Him at <hi>York</hi> on Friday the ſeventeenth of June, by the Lord <hi>Howard,</hi> Sir <hi>Hugh Cholmely,</hi> Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton,</hi> Though He might refer the Petitioners to His two laſt Declarations, wherein moſt of the Particulars in this Petition are fully an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, or might refuſe to give any Anſwer at all, rill He had received ſatisfaction in thoſe high Indigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties He hath ſo often complained of, and demanded Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice for; Yet that all the World may ſee how deſirous His Majeſtie is to leave no Act which ſeemes to carry the Reputation of both his houſes of Parliament, and in the leaſt degree to reflect upon His Majeſties Iuſtice and Honour, unanſwered; Is graciouſly pleaſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne this Anſwer:</p>
            <p>That if the Petition mentioned to be Preſented to both Houſes of Parliament had been annexed to this now delivered to Him, His Majeſtie might have diſcerned the number and the quality of the Petitioners, which His Majeſtie hath great reaſon to beleeve was not in trueth ſo conſiderable as is pretended: For His Majeſtie aſſures you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That He hath never refuſed any Petition ſo atteſted as that would be thought to be; But His Majeſtie well
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:156781:4"/>remembers, that on the third of Iune, when there was upon His Majeſties Summons, the greateſt, and the moſt cheerfull concourſe of people that ever was beheld of one County, appearing before Him at <hi>York,</hi> a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man (one Sir <hi>Thomas Fayrfax</hi>) offered in that great Confluence a Petition to His Majeſtie, which His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie ſeeing to be avowed by no man but himſelf, and the generall and univerſall Acclamations of the people ſeeming to diſclaim it, did not receive, conceiving it not to be of ſo publike a nature, as to be fit to be preſented or received in that place: And His Majeſtie is moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, (and in that muſt appeal to thoſe were then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent) that what ever the ſubſtance of that Petition was, it was not conſented to by any conſiderable num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Gentry, or Freeholders of this County; but ſolicited by a few, mean, inconſiderable perſons, and diſliked, and viſibly diſcountenanced by the great Body of the known Gentry, Clergie, and Inhabitants of this whole Countie: And if the matter of that Petition was ſuch as is ſuggeſted in this, His Majeſtie hath great reaſon to beleeve it was framed and contrived (as many others of ſuch nature have been) in <hi>London,</hi> not in <hi>Yorkſhire;</hi> For ſure no Gentleman of quality and underſtanding of this County, would talk of His great Preparations of Arms, and other warlike Proviſions, to the great Terrour and Amazement of His peaceable Subjects, when they are witneſſes of the violent taking His Arms from Him, and ſtopping all waies for bringing more to Him: And if there were no greater Terrour and Amazement of His Majeſties peaceable Subjects in other places by ſuch Preparations and Proviſions, there would be no more cauſe to complaine of a great decay of Trade and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce there, then is in this place<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But His M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="7 letters">
                  <desc>〈7 letters〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:156781:5"/>hath ſo great an aſſurance of the Fidelity and generall Affections of His good Subjects of this County, (which He hopes will prove exemplar over His whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom) that He hath great cauſe to beleeve, That they do rather complain of His Majeſties Confidence, and of His Slowneſſe; That whileſt there is ſuch endeavour abroad to raiſe Horſe, and to provide Arms againſt His Majeſtie, and that endeavour put in execution, His Majeſtie truſts ſo much to the Iuſtice of His Cauſe, and the Affections of His people, and neglects to provide ſtrength to aſſiſt that Iuſtice, and to protect thoſe Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections.</p>
            <p>For any Affronts offered by the Earl of <hi>Lindſey,</hi> or the Lord <hi>Savill</hi> to thoſe who intended to petition His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie; His Majeſtie wiſhes that both His Houſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament would have examined that Information, and the credit of the Informers, with that gravity and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration, as in Caſes which concern the Innoceuce and Honour of Perſons of ſuch quality hath been accuſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, before they had Proſcribed two Peers of the Realm, and expoſed them (as much as in them lay) to the rage and fury of the people, under the Character of being <hi>Enemies to the Common-wealth,</hi> A brand newly found out (and of no Legall ſignification) to incenſe the people by, and with which the ſimplicity of former times was not acquainted; And then His Majeſtie hath ſome reaſon to beleeve, they would have found themſelves as much abuſed in the report concerning thoſe Lords, as He is ſure they are in thoſe which tell them <hi>of the Reſort of great numbers and diſcontented Perſons to Him,</hi> and of the other particulars mentioned to be in that Petition; Whereas they who obſerve what reſort is here to His Majeſtie, well know it to be of the prime Gentlemen of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:156781:5"/>all the Counties in <hi>England,</hi> whom nothing but the love of Religion, the care of the Laws, and Liberties of the Kingdom, beſides their Affection to His Perſon, could engage into great Iourneys, Trouble and expence, Men of as precious Reputation, and as exemplary Lives, as this Nation hath any, whoſe aſſiſtance His Majeſtie knows He muſt not expect, if He ſhould have the leaſt Deſigne againſt Honour and Iuſtice; And ſuch wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes His Majeſtie deſires to have of all His Actions.</p>
            <p>For the declining all other Counſells and the Vniting His Confidence to His Parliament, His Majeſtie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires both His Houſes of Parliament ſeriouſly and ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to conſider, that it is not the name of a great or little Councell that makes the Reſults of that Councell juſt or unjuſt; neither can the imputation upon His Majeſtie of not being adviſed by His Parliament (eſpecially ſince all their Actions and all their Orders are expoſed to the Publique view) long miſlead His good Subjects, except in truth they ſee ſome particular ſound advice neceſſarie to the Peace and happineſſe of the Common-wealth diſeſteemed by His Majeſtie, and ſuch an inſtance He is moſt aſſured, neither can nor ſhall be given, and that they will think it merit in His Majeſtie from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth to reject ſuch Counſell as would perſwade Him to make Himſelf none of the three Eſtates, by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving up His negative voice to allow them a Power ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior to that which the Law hath given Him, whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it pleaſeth the major part preſent of both Houſes to ſay, that He doth not diſcharge His truſt as He ought, and to ſubject His, and His Subjects unqueſtionable Right and Propriety to their Votes, without and againſt Law, upon the meer pretence of neceſſitie. And His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie muſt appeal to all the World, who it is that endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:156781:6"/>to divide the joynt dutie of His Subiects, His Majeſtie who requires nothing but what their own du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, guided by the infallible Rule of the Law, leads them to do, or they who by Orders and Votes (oppoſite and contradictory to Law, Cuffome, preſident and reaſon) ſo confound the affections and underſtandings of His good Subjects, that they know not how to behave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with honeſtie and ſafetie, whileſt their Conſcience will not ſuffer them to ſubmit to the one, nor their ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to apply themſelves to the other. It is not the bare ſaying that His Maieſties Actions are againſt the Law (with which He is reproached in this Petition, as if He departed from His often Proteſtations to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) muſt conclude Him, there being no one ſuch parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular in that Petition alledged, of which His Majeſtie is in the leaſt degree guiltie, whether the ſame reverence and eſteem be paid by you to the Law (except your own Votes be judge) needs no other Evidence, then thoſe many, very many Orders publiſhed in Print, both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Church and State, thoſe long Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſeverall perſons without hearing them upon generall information, and the great and unlimited Fees to your Officers, worſe then the Impriſonment, and the Arbitrary cenſure upon them when they are admitted to be heard; Let the Law be judge by whom it is vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated.</p>
            <p>For that part of the Petition which ſeems to accuſe His Majeſtie of a purpoſe to diſſolve this Parliament contrary to the Act for the Continuance) by Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away the Lords and great Officers, whoſe attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance is neceſſary, which His Majeſtie, well knows to be a new Calumny, by which the Grand Contrivers of ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine for the State hope to ſeduce the mindes of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:156781:6"/>from their affection to, or into Jealouſie of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, as if He meant this way to bring this Parliament (which may be the caſe of all Parliaments) to nothing; it is not poſſible for His Majeſtie more to expreſſe His af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to, and His Reſolution for the Freedom, Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and Frequencie of Parliaments, then He hath done; And who ever conſiders how viſible it muſt be to His Majeſtie, that it is impoſſible for Him to ſubſiſt without the affections of His People, and that thoſe affections cannot poſſibly be preſerved or made uſe of but by Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, cannot give the leaſt credit, or have the leaſt ſuſpition, that His Majeſtie would chuſe any other way to the happineſſe He deſires for Himſelf and His Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, but by Parliaments. But for His calling the Lords hither, or any others abſenting themſelves, who have not been called, who ever conſiders the Cumults (which no Votes or Declaration can make to be no Til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults) by which His Majeſtie was driven away, and many Members of either Houſe in danger of their lives, the demanding the names of thoſe Lords who would not conſent to their Propoſitions by Meſſage from the Houſe of Commons delivered at the Barr by Maſter <hi>Hollis,</hi> with that moſt tumultuous Petition in the Name of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands (among many other of the ſame kinde) directed to the Houſe of Commions, and ſent up by them to the Houſe of Lords, taking notice of the prevalence of a malignant Faction, which made abortive all their good Motions; which tended to the Peace and Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility of the Kingdom, deſiring that thoſe noble Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies of the Houſe of Peers who concurred with them in their happy Votes, might be earneſtly deſired to joyn with that honourable Houſe, and to ſit and Vote as one entire Body, profeſſing that unleſſe ſome ſpeedy
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:156781:7"/>remedy were taken for the removeall of all ſuch obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions as hindred the happy progreſſe of their great en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, their Petitioners ſhould not reſt in quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but ſhould be inforced to lay hold on the next re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy which was at hand to remove the diſturbers of their Peace, and (want and neceſſity breaking the bounds of modeſty) not to leave any means unaſſayed for their relief, adding that the cry of the Poor and needy was, that ſuch Perſons who were the Obſtacles of their Peace, and hinderers of the happy proceedings of this Parliament might be forthwith publikely decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, whoſe removeall they conceived would put a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod to theſe diſtractions; upon which a great number of Lords departing, the Vote in order to the Ordinance concerning the <hi>Militia</hi> was immediatly paſt, though it had been twice before put to the Queſtion, and rejected by the Votes of much the major part of that Houſe. And whoever conſiders the ſtrange Orders, Votes and Declarations which have ſince paſſed, to which who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld not conſent, that is, with freedom and liberty of language and reaſon profeſſe againſt, was in danger of Cenſure and Impriſonment, will not blame Our Care in ſending for them, or theirs in coming, or abſenting themſelves from being involved in ſuch Concluſions. Neither will it be any objection that they ſtayed there long after any Tumults were, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that the Tumults drave them not away: If every day produced Orders and Reſolutions as illegall as, and indeed but the effects of the Tumults, there was no cauſe to doubt the ſame power would be ready to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent any Oppoſition to thoſe Orders after they were made, which had made way and preparation for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of them, and ſo whoſoever conceived himſelf
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:156781:7"/>in danger of future Tumults (againſt which there is not the leaſt proviſion) was driven away by thoſe which were paſt; And His Majeſtie hath more reaſon to won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at thoſe who ſtay behinde, after all His Legall Power is Voted from Him, and all the People told, That he might be with modeſty and duty enough depoſed, then any man hath at thoſe who have been willing to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw themſelves from the place where ſuch deſperate and dangerous Poſitions are avowed; which His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie doth not mention with the leaſt thought of leſſening the Power or Validity of any Act to which He hath given His Aſſent this Parliament; All and every of which He ſhall as inviolably obſerve, as He looks to have His own Rights preſerved, but to ſhew by what means ſo many ſtrange Orders have of late been made, And to ſhew how earneſtly His Majeſtie deſires to be preſent at, and to receive Advice from both Houſes of Parliament (againſt whom it ſhall never be in the power of a Malignant Party to incenſe his Majeſtie) His Majeſtie again offers His conſent, that both Houſes may be Adjourned to another Place, which may be thought convenient, where His Majeſtie will be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and doubts not but the Members of either Houſe will make a full Appearance; And even the Intermiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion which muſt attend ſuch an Adjournment may not be the leaſt means of recovering that temper which is neceſſary for ſuch Debates.</p>
            <p>And this His Majeſtie conceives to be ſo very neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, that if the mindes and inclinations of every Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of either Houſe were equally compoſed, the Licence is ſo great, that the mean people about <hi>London</hi> and the Suburbs have taken, that both for the Liberty and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnity of Parliament, that Convention for a time ſhould
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:156781:8"/>be in another place. And ſure how much ſoever the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and ſecurity of this Kingdom depends on Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, it will never be thought, that thoſe Parliaments muſt of neceſſity be at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Majeſties Confidence is no leſſe then he hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed (and hath great cauſe to expreſſe) in the affections of this County, an inſtance of which affections all men know, His Guard (which is not extraordinary) to be, and wonders that ſuch a legall Guard at His own charge, for His Perſon, (within twenty miles of a rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, and of an Army in pay againſt Him) ſhould be object<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by thoſe, who for ſo many moneths, and in a place of known and confeſſed ſecurity, have without and againſt Law kept a Guard for themſelves at the charge of the Common-wealth, and upon that ſtock of money which was given for the reliefe of the miſerable and bleeding condition of <hi>Ireland,</hi> or the payment of the great debt due to Our Kingdom of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the reſort of Papiſts to the Court his Majeſties great care for the prevention thereof is notoriouſly known, that when He was informed two or three of his intended Guard were of that Religion, He gave eſpeciall direction, with expreſſions of His diſpleaſure, that they ſhould be immediatly diſcharged, and provided that no Perſon ſhould attend on him under that Relation, but ſuch as took, the oathes of Allegiance and Supremary, that He commanded the Sheriffe to proceed with all ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity according to the Law againſt all Papiſts that ſhould come within five miles of the Court, and if not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this, there be any Papiſts neer the Court, (which his Majeſtie aſſures you he knowes not, nor hath heard but by this Petition) He doth hereby Command them to depart, and declares to all Officers and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:156781:8"/>of Iuſtice, that they ſhall proceed fleictly againſt them according to the Law, and as they will anſwer the contrary at their perils.</p>
            <p>For the language and behaviour of the <hi>Cavaliers</hi> (a word by what miſtake ſoever it ſeemes much in disfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour) there hath not been the leaſt complaint here, and therefore it is probable the fault was not found in this County. Neither can His Majeſtie imag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e what is meant by the mention of any men thruſt upon them in ſuch Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ultations and Propoſitions as His Majeſtie makes to this County, who are neither by there Fortune or Reſidence any part of it, and therefore can make us Anſwer to it.</p>
            <p>To conclude, His Majeſtle aſſures you He hath never refuſed to receive any Petition, whether you have or no, your ſelves beſt know, and will conſider what Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it will be to you of Iuſtice or Ingenuity to receive all Petitions how ſenſleſſe and ſcandalous ſoever of one kinde, under pretence of underſtanding the good peoples mindes and affections, and not onely refuſe the Petition, but puniſh the Petitioners of another kinde, under co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour that it is a crime, that they are not ſatisfied with your ſenſe, as if you were onely truſted by the people of one opinion, to take all pains to publiſh and print Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which agree with your wiſhes, though they were never preſented, and to uſe the ſame Induſtry and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to keep thoſe that indeed were preſented and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowed from being publiſhed (though by Our own Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority) becauſe the Argument is not pleaſant to you; To pretend Impartiality and Infallibility, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the greateſt paſſion and affection in the Order of your Proceeding, and no leſſe errour and miſ-under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in your Iudgements and Reſolutions. He doth
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:156781:9"/>remember well the obligation of His Truſt, and of His Oath, and deſires that you will do ſo too, and your own ſolemn Vow and Proteſtation, and then you wil not only think it convenient, but neceſſary to give His Majeſtie a ful Reparation for all the ſcandalls laid upon Him, and all the ſcandalous Poſitions made againſt Him, and that it is leſſe diſhonor to retract errors, then by avowing to confeſſe the malice of them, &amp; will ſee this to be the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt way for the preſervation of the Proteſtant Religion, the redemption of Our Brethren in <hi>Ireland,</hi> the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and proſperity of your ſelves and of all Our Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and of the Dignity and Freedom of Parliament.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
